hello pilots of the internet and welcome
back to foldable flight i know that it
has been a minute since i've posted any
videos to this channel
but i hope that you will forgive me
because i'm about to teach you
one of the very best paper airplanes
that i have ever
designed ballasta is an incredible paper
airplane that locks
in this very aerodynamic
three-dimensional shape
and because of that this plane easily
flies over 100 feet
even better than that this plane is easy
to fold and it's my belief that anyone
watching this video with just a little
bit of practice can fold this plane
now as with most of my planes i have
designed a template for it so if you
support me on patreon you can fold a
plane that looks like this
rather than using a plain sheet of paper
and with that said let's see this plane
in flight and then i'll teach you how to
fold it
[Applause]
[Music]
all you will need in order to fold
ballasta is an eight and a half by 11 or
a4 sheet of paper and we will begin by
folding the right edge
to the left edge
the next step is to go ahead and open
your paper up and flip it over so that
you have a mountain crease here in the
center and we're going to fold the top
two inches of the paper down and this is
just an estimation
anything close to two inches is great
now go ahead and flip your paper back
over and we're going to fold this top
edge here into the center but we want to
leave a little bit of a gap so make this
edge
parallel to the center crease but don't
take it all the way to it i like to
leave a gap
of about an eighth of an inch
okay and i'll do the same thing on the
other side and i'm just trying to
visually match up my gaps you could
fold the paper in half like so
and bookmatch it but i find that i'm
actually just as accurate if i do this
just visually
and your plane should look like this
now i'm going to go ahead and fold this
to this edge here so i'm just taking
this outer edge
and i really want to control this layer
as
i fold this in so that the layer doesn't
move
so pin that down with one hand fold it
in to
that edge just like so
and when you're content with your
alignment go ahead and place your crease
now go ahead and do the same thing on
the other side i pin it down with my
right hand
fold in with my left
and your plane should now look like this
next go ahead and fold the outer edge in
once again and we're lining it up
with this new edge that we have here
and the same thing you really want to
control that layer as you're folding in
like so
and then you make your crease on the
outside and now we're going to do that
on the left side as well
and this is obviously very thick at the
front so you really got to work on that
as you place your crease i know it's a
little bit difficult just because of the
thickness of the paper
and hopefully your plane now looks like
this and it's nice and symmetrical
if it's not symmetrical that's okay i
think you'll be fine
anyways and we're ready now to go ahead
and fold the plane in half
putting all these layers into the middle
of the plane
and we can set it on its side like so
we're ready to fold the wings
now we're going to basically be folding
this edge here
to land on the bottom edge but because
this area at the front is so thick we
actually need to start
our wing crease more like here rather
than all the way at the front of the
plane
and i'm going to land the back edge of
the wing right on that point there
and now that i've done that on one side
i'm going to flip it over but first i
want to actually
unfold that wing because it's very hard
to fold both wings at the same time
and now i'm going to fold this wing to
match starting my wing crease at the
same exact point
and because i don't actually have that
other wing folded i can't just book
match this one to it so before i really
place my crease in the back
i want to make sure that that crease is
going to end up at the same point
as the other one and you can see this is
just a tiny bit higher
in the back so i'm going to lower that
crease just a little bit
before i place it and then i'll
reinforce my crease all the way up to
the front
like so and you can see my plane is
looking pretty good from the back now
and we are almost done but we still need
to fold the locking mechanism for the
plane
so i'm going to set it on its side again
and i'm going to fold from this point
right here
where this layer is intersecting the
bottom edge
and i'm going to fold to this point
where that crease is intersecting the
back edge so
those two reference points i'm folding
from one to the other
and i'm folding both tabs here at the
back
and once i've done that i can open up
one of the tabs and i'm going to fold
this little triangle that goes
past this edge here just over
that layer and then i can tuck it into
this pocket
so you can see i've folded this now i'm
just folding it into
that pocket there
like so and now i'll go ahead and fold
this little triangle
over the edge of the layer on top of it
and i'm ready now to tuck this tab into
the same pocket that i tucked to the
first one
so i'm just swinging that there and
kind of curling this enough that i can
tuck that point
into that pocket
and now these two tabs are kind of one
tab and i can just tuck that tab
into this big pocket at the back of the
plane
and now once i reinforce my wing creases
and set my wings to the appropriate
angle which i think is just
very very slightly upward
so it has just a tiny tiny bit of
dihedral angle
flat is fine too now this is a finished
plane
the asymmetry of this locking mechanism
though
will make the plane tend to spiral a
little bit and so if it's spiraling
clockwise so in this direction here you
can
bend the back edge of the left wing up
just slightly
and the rudder just slightly to the left
and that will help to compensate
for the spin if it's spinning in the
opposite direction you do just the
opposite bending the back edge of the
right wing up
and the rudder slightly to the right and
with that
good luck flying your plane
you